Guide to the Carroll and Helen Yerkes Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Carroll and Helen Yerkes Papers
1869-1971
RG 153
Yale University Divinity School Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
Letters and collected material document the work of the Presbyterian Church in Shantung Province, China from 1869 to the 1940s. Carroll and Helen Yerkes were American Presbyterian missionaries in Shantung Province from 1904 to 1925. The parents of Helen Nevius Eckard Yerkes were Presbyterian missionaries stationed in Chefoo from 1869 to 1874.
Yerkes, Carroll Harvey, 1876-1971
Yerkes, Helen
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth Y. Kline.
Biographical / Historical
1876 Aug 18 Born in Fox Chase, Philadelphia, PA
1895-1896 Attended International Conventions of Christian Endeavor at which he heard Dwight L. Moody, Robert E. Speer, Amos R. Wells and others who influenced his life.
1901 A.B. degree, Lafayette College
1903 Worked with settlers on the prairie of No. Dakota
1904 A.M. degree, Princeton Theological Seminary
1904 Jul 12 Married Helen Nevius Eckard (1876-1967)
1904 Sep 12 Arrived in Shanghai as missionary for the Presbyterian Board of Foreign Missions
1905 Opened station at Yihsien, Shantung Province
1912 Furlough
1921 Honorary D.D., Lafayette
1925 Returned to U.S. because of Helen Yerkes' health
1925-1957 Served as pastor of various churches in New Jersey and Pennsylvania
1971 Apr 19 Died in Seattle, Washington
Scope and Contents
The Yerkes papers document the work of the Presbyterian Church in the Shantung Province of China from 1869-1874 when Helen Yerkes' parents were stationed in Chefoo and from 1904-1950. Although they left China in 1925, Yerkes stayed in contact with his missionary and Chinese friends. Yerkes was involved with evangelical work as well as the administrative tasks of running the station. Among his duties, he served on the China Council and acted as treasurer of the station. From 1923 until his departure from China, he worked with the American Consulate, R.P. Tenney, to secure the release of foreign captives after the wreck of the "Blue Express" on May 6, 1923 and continued to supply information about the bandit situation in his area.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1870-1950
II. Collected Material, 1904-1941, n.d.
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1904-1971
IV. Photographs, ca.1870-1954
Presbyterian Church -- Missions -- China; Missionaries; Eckard, L. W. (Leighton Wilson), 1845-1925; Yerkes, Carroll Harvey, 1876-1971; Yerkes, Helen
- Correspondence, 1870-1950; Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Letters from Helen Yerkes' father, Leighton W. Eckard, to his family, from Chefoo, 1870, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To "Dear Father" (Leighton Eckard?), 1905-1914, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
    - Other family members, 1917-1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence
    - Allison, Abbott, 1925-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Butler - Cunningham, 1924-1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - E - Frame, 1925-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Gordon - Lowrie, 1922-1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Romig - Soderberg, 1918-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Thompson - Winter, unidentified, 1925-1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Circular letters (Shantung Mission), 1918-1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Collected Material, 1904-1941, n.d.; Series II
  - Bible in Chinese, misc. items, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - China Council Ad Interim Committee minutes, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The China Council Bulletin, 1926, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The China Council of the Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A., 1925, 1927, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Chinagram", 1929 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chinese documents - calling cards, correspondence, money, etc. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Chinese posters and prints, including "The Chinese Family", Mission tract "colored by one of my school boys", Biblical quotations, anatomical diagram, etc. (Box OVd3)
  - Print depicting "God of Agriculture and Silk Worm Culture", unidentified print (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cities Evangelization Centers reports, 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "First Chinese Mission Tract" (by Leighton Eckard), ca. 1869 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Government proclamation re. missionaries, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 1920-1940, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Newsclippings, 1904-1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Shantung Mission Council, 1925, 1926, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Station reports: Chefoo, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Station reports: Ichoufu, 1925-1932 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Station reports: Tenghsien, 1925, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Station reports: Yihsien (incl. general China Station information, building diagrams, staff resumes), 1918-1941, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Station reports: Yihsien (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1904-1971; Series III
  - Commission, marriage certificate, passports, Chinese documents, etc., 1904-1925 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Letters of reference re. pastorate, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Material re. Yerkes' role in the release of captives from the wreck of the "Blue Express" on May 6, 1923; incl. information re. bandit situation around Yihsien (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Recollections of a Long Life" (autobiographical) and other biographical material and tributes, 1963-1971 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Photographs, ca.1870 -1954; Series IV
  - Sunday School class of Leighton Eckard, ca. 1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Family and friends, 1905-1923, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Missionary groups, 1904-1918 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Scenes from Ichoufu, Yihsien, Shanghai; coal mining, railroads, agriculture, markets, etc., ca. 1905-1925 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Student groups and hospital scenes, local church members (Yihsien and outstations), ca. 1911-1925 (Box 3, Folder 39)